Guide to the Jewish Communal Registers (Pinkese kehilah) Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Additional material, 1756?-1945; Accession 2015-M-005
  - Russia
    - Pinḳas ḥevrah biḳur ḥolim ṿe-hakhnasat kalah, 1888-1928 (Box 11)
      Register of the society for visiting the sick and providing dowries for brides in the Jewish community of Astrakhanʹ, Russia. Contains mission statements, by-laws, and the names of leaders and members, with women given autonomy to provide for the needs of the brides. The society was founded 1 Tamuz 648 [1888]. Dates of death of some of the members were added subsequently, as late as 20 Tevet 688 [1928]. At the back of the register there are two statements of fathers dated in the 1892 and 1895 testifying that their daughters were playing with other girls and accidently started bleeding. Apparently this was to prevent accusations concerning loss of virginity. Manuscript, ink on vellum. In Hebrew and Yiddish. The title page is illuminated with an intricate multi-colored drawing of an arched gate with columns on either side, six pointed stars, vases with flowers, and geometric patterns all enclosed within a decorative border. 20 pages; 30 centimeters. Original embossed leather binding with title stamped on front cover in cyrillic letters.
  - Slovakia
    - Taḳanot le-ḥevrah ḳadisha be-yishuv Ahaya, 1884-circa 1930 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      Register of by-laws (takanot) of a Jewish communal welfare society from the village of Ahaya in the Austro-Hungarian Empire, probably the place known today as Dolný Ohaj, Slovakia. At the time this volume was written, this village was in Hungary and was called Nagyóhaj. The title page is dated 645 [1884 or 1885]. Later entries in the volume include dates into the first third of the twentieth century. In Yiddish. 1 volume; 43 centimeters.
    - Document regarding a bequest to the Jewish community of Liptovský Mikuláš, 1906 (Box 12, Folder 2)
      Disposition of the last will and testament of Hercz Fülöp (Phillip Hertz) bequeathing a third of his estate to the Jewish community of Liptószentmiklós, Hungary (since 1918, Liptovský Mikuláš, Slovakia) and two-thirds to its Hevra Kadisha. The document includes the by-laws of the fund established by this bequest. Although Mr. Hercz died in 1887, this document is dated March 18, 1906. In Hungarian. Mimeographed with a few handwritten additions. [8] pages; 34 centimeters.
    - Pinḳas Ḳehal ʻAdat Yeshurun de-k.k. Nyiṭraʻ, Bulk, 1760-1810 1756?-1948; 1760-1810 (Box 13)
      Register from the Jewish community of Nitra. Although not a large city, Nitra was an important center of Jewish life in the Austro-Hungarian Empire in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries. This register includes by-laws of the congregation, entries concerning local conditions, issues and controversies, and demographic information such as occupations of members of the community. The name of the town appears in several different spellings within this volume. Manuscript in Hebrew and Yiddish. Approximately 200 pages; 32 centimeters.
    - Pinḳas ḳehilat Bisṭrits, 1833-1881 (Box 14)
      Register of a Jewish community now known as Považská Bystrica, Slovakia and formerly as Vag Besztercze (Hungarian) and Waag Bistritz (German). The title page is lacking. The first page (p.2) contains a poem in Hebrew praising the faithful founders of the community. It is signed in an acrostic by the scribe Kalman Kohn. Pages 3-9 contain several introductory statements in German, Hebrew and Yiddish signed by officials and leaders of the community. Following these is an index to over one hundred by-laws of the congregation, which are written in Yiddish script on pages 10b-19. The by-laws cover such topics as obligations of community members, prayers and synagogue protocols, and disbursement of funds for communal and charitable needs. After the by-laws are several more official declarations in various languages including four pages written in Latin, signed and stamped with red wax seals. The bulk of the volume contains individual pages for each member of the community. The members' names are written in large Hebrew letters. Below each name are notations concerning the member's contributions and the assigned seats in the men's and women's sections of the synagogue. 184 leaves; 43 centimeters. Original leather binding.
    - Pinḳas ḳehilat Bisṭrits, 1833-1875 (Box 15)
      The register seems to belong to the same set as the other pinkas from Považská Bystrica, Slovakia. It includes records of meetings signed by leaders of the community, contributions and expenditures. There are diagrams showing the men's and women's sections of the synagogue. Parts of the manuscript are in Yiddish, Hebrew, German, Latin, and Hungarian. [48] leaves; 43 centimeters. Original leather binding.
    - Zeh ha-pinḳas shayakh le-Ḥ.Ḳ. poh Ṭernoy.., 1800-1939 (Box 16)
      Register of the Hevrah Kadisha from Trnava (Nagyszombat; Tyrnau), Slovakia. Although Jews first settled in Trnava in the late middles ages, persecution and expulsion followed, and only in the late 18th century did restrictions begin to ease. The register is dated the first of the month of Heshvan of the year 561 (1800). The small Jewish community had just established a cemetery and burial society in Trnava. This volume contains the records of the burial society: its by-laws (takanot), members, contributions, and accounts of important historical events in the community. In Yiddish and Hebrew. Approximately 400 leaves; 40 centimeters.
  - United States
    - Pinḳas de-ḥevrah ḳedoshah me-ḥevrah Ahavat Yiśraʼel, Bulk, 1923-1933 1923-1988 (1923-1933 bulk); 1923-1933 (Box 17)
      Register of the Hevrah Kadisha (burial society) "Ahavat Yisrael," located at 1372-4 Gates Avenue in Brooklyn, New York, The address is included on the cover and the title page. The title page is calligraphed and illuminated in gold and colored ink with architectural columns, rampant lions and other decorative elements. The entries are written in Yiddish and Hebrew in square characters. The volume includes an introduction (page 5), takanot (by-laws) of the Society relating to official duties (pages 15-23), history of the Hevra Kadisha and lists of officers and members (pages 43-59, 129-135), a second title page (page 461) followed by detailed descriptions of practices related to accompanying, purifying, and dressing the deceased, and yahrtzeits of members (463-497). The Hevrah Kadisha was founded on 15 Kislev 5676 (December 1915). This volume is dated 683 [1923] with additional entries added in subsequent years, one as late as 1988. Original binding, red Morocco, spine detached. 500 pages, including numerous blanks; 40 cm.
- Additional material, 1754; Accession 2016-M-010
  - Pinḳas ḳehilat Mehrin, 1754 (Box 1)
    General
    Community ledgers of Moravia. Manuscript in Hebrew and Judeo-German, written in a cursive Aschkenazic hand on paper. The Tzvi Hirsh Shapiro of Munkacs copy, with his stamps throughout. Title page read: "General Policy Process, Commercial Order for the Judenschaft in Moravia, 1754." Divided into three sections and subsections. Large portion consists of 360 regulations (Takanoth) relating to religious affairs and appropriate social behavior, also with many laws pertaining to synagogue life. It is possible that this was written for the community of Nikolsburg.--Description in vendor's catalog.
- Additional Material, Accession 2016-M-026
  - Pinkas Oldenzaal, 1800-1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Manuscript register book from the Jewish community of Oldenzaal, the Netherlands. Ink on paper, with original vellum binding. The title page is decorated with drawings of two cherubs standing atop columns supporting the word "Pinkas" [register book], with a crown on the top. The book, dated 561 [1800 or 1801], was made to raise funds to build a synagogue. According to the Jewish Historical Museum in Amsterdam, "a division in the community [of Oldenzaal] in 1800 led to a decision to found a second synagogue. The new house of worship was consecrated in 1802." The first section of the book contains pages with members' names at the top and foldable cut-out tabs to record their pledges on the Sabbath or holidays without writing. Another section of the book records well over a century--from the beginning of the nineteenth century until autumn 1941--of the members of the community selected to receive honors on holidays.
  - Trieste manuscript, Circa 19th Century (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Manuscript in Hebrew containing instructions for observing the Sabbath and Festivals according to the traditions of the Jewish community of Trieste, Italy.
  - Pinkas Lugo, 1764-1825 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    This volume is mostly written in Italian with names of people and Hebrew passages. The majority of the ledger records various communal affairs depicting daily life of Italian Jewry from the mid-18th century. Also contains interesting diocumentation of Eretz-Israeli emissaries who visited the community. On the last leaves of the volume are titles and lists of donations to Eretz Israel funds, Kupat Hebron, the needy residents of Jerusalem Safed and Tiberias.
  - Pinkas Nikolsburg, 1651 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    The manuscript is in Hebrew and contains takanot (by-laws) of the Jewish community of Nikolsburg, Moravia (now known as Mikulov in the Czech Republic). It includes regulations regarding the community life in Nikolsburg. The first few pages are missing, and the text begins with Takanah number 39. The colophon is dated 4 Shevat 411 (1651).